software engineering radio episode 79
small memory software
[Music]
welcome everybody to this yet another
episode of software engineering radio
this episode is part of our embedded
series and we're going to talk about
small memory software before we
introduce our guests or interviewees I
just like to say a quick thanks to a6
that how come the organizers of the Opie
conference because they gave us this
neat little room here where we can
record stuff in a quiet atmosphere as
part of the LP 2007 conference it's
actually not easy to get these kinds of
rooms at conferences because everybody
wants one so it's really cool that we
actually got one so welcome Charles and
James to the SU radio podcast why don't
you introduce yourself and talk a little
about a little bit about your background
hello I'm Charles where I run a small
software development house in the north
of England pen relyin and small bit
expanding and we specialize in software
for mobile phones my background was as a
consultant in object technology teaching
and working with people when in the days
when C++ and Java was still a really new
concept and as part of that I did a lot
of work with Symbian as a technical lead
and when James and I were casting around
for something to write a book on we
realized that one thing that we really
shared was small memory this having
worked with small machines and working
with small machines over to James
I'm James Nobel I'm professor of
computer science at Victoria University
of Wellington in New Zealand and in fact
for the last few months now I've been on
sabbatical in Europe I'm currently a
academic visitor at Microsoft Research
in Cambridge which is certainly an
interesting place to be and as Charles
said I worked with Charles on design
patterns for a number of years and we
thought that there was important best
practice the kind of things that
programmers do and the programmers have
been doing for a number of years that in
some ways we've been lost to the
object-oriented community with the
emergence of lots of small devices
like that rather neat recorder you've
gotta Marcus issues of memory sighs
really don't go away even as the
technology continues improving and we
were interested in documenting and
making that practice available to
developers more generally in fact I've
been finding when when we first wrote
the book we believed that we were
talking about something that was if not
obsolete it was rapidly becoming
something that nobody would be
interested in we did it for the fun of
it actually as I've been you know giving
talks on the subject I'm finding that
far from being obsolete this is more and
more becoming mainstream small memory
software is becoming something that that
I get bigger and bigger audiences for
and it is you know ubiquitous computing
and many millions of small machines is
something that that is becoming
mainstream so you wrote the book when in
which year we actually published it in
2000 right and now we have 2007 ioan
you're invited to the LP conference and
to talk about small memory so that's
kind of one of the proofs that the small
memory stuff is not getting obsolete
exactly okay so what is small memory
software I would say it is anything any
software where the memory size be a disk
or Ram is a consideration
mm-hm now it's surprising how many how
many situations that is actually not
true most most workstation applications
really running out of memory can be
considered completely fatal you don't
have to worry about it if it happens
something's gone horribly wrong now but
in in any environment with less than
about a Meg availab megabyte of memory
available for processing it's quite
likely that you'll have to think a
little bit about memory management
certainly all of the Symbian devices we
work with certainly anything embedded
certainly anything with its own software
that's produced in the millions is going
to have somebody saying well what if we
made the memory slightly smaller yeah
that's this typical effect and embedded
software that you don't necessarily have
the development cost us the driving
factor but the per unit production cost
so better optimize the software for one
more year paying people and get the
amount of memory lowered right there's
another interesting but relatively small
application area where once again we
found these two techniques being used
and it's a bit of a surprising one which
is in systems that are doing an awful
lot of processing so funnily enough
people doing batch processing on
mainframes or in certain cases doing
scientific computation also have
problems with memory for the mainframe
stuff it's because once you're trying to
do millions of transactions a minute you
said we can't afford to allocate very
much CPU or very much memory to each
individual transaction
Dave Thomas from oti once described the
sort of big IBM mainframes as you know
just very very big embedded computers
very very big embedded systems and the
other one of people doing scientific
computing if you're doing genomics or
some of the grid stuff mean it doesn't
really matter if you've only got you
know two gigabytes of memory shared
amongst 16 some cause if the amount of
data you're trying to handle is really
really huge and that was one of the
surprising things we found that and I
think it's one of the things that
patents can do quite well is recognize
the real problem here is dealing with
memory of limitations as Charles says if
you're programming and you have to care
about memory mm-hmm it doesn't matter if
you're working on a very small machine
you know trying to fit a little bit more
data in than you've got or even if
you're working a very big machine
because chances are you may be dealing
with huge amounts of data so it's
somewhat ironic in that it's the desktop
applications of the odd ones out because
typically in the desktop applications
one of the defining characteristics
there is there's one we're willing to
just ignore the fact that we might run
out of memory basically well page to the
disk and if it isn't fools that fills up
on your laptop well you're basically you
go and buy a new one yeah yeah if the
disk fills up with only paging there
might be a more systematic error well
you go and you buy and buy a new duel
call a new tab so one should distinguish
of course memory leaks which are an
issue
merriment from this kind of small memory
software which reminds me what was that
question you asked Charles at the start
of his interview that what his laptop
was doing oh yeah at each other blue
screen actually yes we've done
interviews about like patterns books
before and the way we've done this
typically and I think which works quite
well is that we're first given overview
over the different like parts chapter
sections in the book that covered
different kinds of patterns different
areas of concern and then we dig into
the areas and look at some of the
patterns in more detail so let's do that
too let's briefly scan over the
different aspects of where you can
actually be aware of memory and what you
should and can do the separation into
categories is is really something we did
after we wrote the patterns yeah so
matter think of these I think of these
as as chapters and the simple one to
start with is small data structures so
designing your code designing your data
structure so they don't take up too much
space but that's also the obvious thing
people think about when they think about
small memories exactly then we started
looking at memory allocation which is
the different ways you can you can
allocate memory be it fixed world
variable there's a whole section that is
slightly more in the region of
application functionality which is using
compression there's different types of
compression then if you're an
environment with secondary storage disk
or anything else then there are a
variety of different ways of doing that
mm-hm
and finally there's a sort of overview
in the way you architect the system
which we've called small architecture a
set of techniques that you can use to
make a whole application or an
application environment work well in in
a small memory situation hmm so it's
funny that you and how do we talk about
these things that you almost mentioned
the chapters backwards flow it was for
five three two one so that's the book I
have the wrong order or why did
why did you mention them in the other
direction I mentioned the other way
because of experience teaching if you
you know I liked I when you're when
you're writing a book in a sense you you
sort of start from the most abstract
most interesting and work towards the
detail when you're teaching you start
with something that everybody can grasp
and then work out to say oh and by the
way this is part of a bigger story but I
suppose were Allison Wesley - come on
offer us a second edition clearly the
way we would make a valuable difference
to the book is that by just changing the
chapter or yeah yeah okay so let's look
at some of the small data structure
patterns oh well shall we start off with
my my favorite little packed data mm-hmm
which is very simple we call it bit
munging mm-hmm you if you have if you
have a lot of data which can be
compressed normalized whatever it might
be you just take it and you pack it into
small number of bits and that way you
can store an awful lot more than you
would if you used four bytes pointers in
the whole the whole gamut of normal fast
programming no so I as an illustration
we considered how you would get an
entire telephone directory into a couple
of megabytes and with a certain amount
of normalization storing figuring out
what telephone numbers actually look
like and using that using features of
that you can do it the obvious example I
think is that typically boolean so I
think our starters bytes although they
only contain one bit of information so
that would be one thing of compressing
significantly well right and and if
you're in in Java it'll probably store
as a word or something it's gotta be an
interesting class the trade-off is
obviously that working with this stuff
is much more complicated than using the
simple data structures yeah you're right
and in some sense though one of the
things we point out in the pattern is
the way in which effectively by either
using macros or access of function right
depending on your language you can try
and abstract that away so that the the
packing the data representation doesn't
sort of infect the rest of it do you
right yes in fact we we typically
recommend we recommend that you have a
class that wrapped
the pack data and so the classes used
the same as if it was not packed and
it's an implementation detail of that
class as to how it actually stores it so
this is interesting that even if you're
doing Java which you might be on a
mobile phone you can still use bit level
packing because what you do is you
basically use bit operations on standard
Java integers to put the information in
and that and you can you can have a Java
class to do things that way yeah but
just in thinking about this if you have
a wrapper class actually and you have
this bit structure that captures a
number of boolean's and then you have a
function that wraps it that returns a
boolean you of course still have a
trench in boolean object created so you
do have an efficient storage but you
have this temporary boolean big-big
object that's passed around that's right
and it's built into Java already of
course you have these capital in classes
wrapping something that's actually only
a four byte integer another thing I
might mention is if you look on the
website small memory comm we have the
sample code that went into the book so
there is an example of Java bit packing
there as indeed of most of the other
patterns okay let's look at the next one
the next one I guess if they're walking
through small data structures is sharing
and once again this is another very
straightforward idea straightforward
pattern which says if you have a common
information used in more than one place
rather than duplicating it in your
program you just share it you store it
once and then get it from whatever
context that you want yeah although this
creates the whole problems of concurrent
access if you're in a concurrent program
so as I'm saying that the concurrency
concern works against this because there
would you you would have liked non
shared data and replication ideally
right so the first question is you know
what do you do if you want to change the
data typically mm-hm
so if you've got concurrent read
accesses you're going to be all right no
problem
which in some sense segues nicely onto
the next pattern which is copy-on-write
exactly yeah yes so if you are sharing
stuff I mean essentially one of the
things the sharing pattern says is you
know you can certainly share stuff
that's immutable mmm how then do you
change the stuff you've sharing okay
well maybe you provide copy-on-write
yeah which is nice because it can give
you the illusion of
every part of the system having their
own private modifiable data structures
but in fact you're only going to use the
memory when you actually need to when
you actually make that chain which is a
form of kind of lazy acquisition of
memory which we'll discuss later I guess
right yeah we will because there are
situations where that that is wise in
their situations where perhaps you don't
want to do that yeah
my favorite amongst the small data
structures is multiple representations
which is where you have one class or
interface and it and it chooses
internally the best representation the
most memory efficient representation for
the particular application so for
example in Symbian I remember the editor
has two modes where it either does it is
either just just formats the bit it's
going to display or it or it's sometimes
formats the whole lot all of the text
it's displaying and that really depends
on how much memory is required and how
big the text is and it makes that
decision on the fly so there are
multiple representations hmm hmm that's
quite fun but obviously it's a lot of
implementation yeah effort to do here
but that's just some extent probably
true for all of these things whenever
you optimize for any kind of
non-functional concern then you always
have to have trade-offs with regards to
the usability the programming model and
convenience certainly yeah shall we move
on to memory allocation right which was
a much bigger topic than it appeared at
first actually probably the most
interesting one from a point of view of
embedded and small systems is fixed
allocation yeah this is an interesting
thing so the idea of I mean by memory
allocation we mean you know in in in see
what happens when you call malloc in
some sense what malloc is doing behind
itself or perhaps the question of
whether you choose to call call malloc
at all or you get the memory some other
way mm-hmm and fixed allocation
basically says make an array of objects
or of of structs whatever whatever you
need to allocate at the start of your
program before
the program really does any work mm-hmm
so that if you know this means that if
your operating environment doesn't have
enough memory to allocate that array
your program simply won't launch so this
is I mean as the title says this is not
a pattern to actually make things
smaller and safe memory it is a way of
handling memory to achieve some other
goal well what's the point by doing why
do why do we do this well that's that's
a really interesting point and this is
what we were arguing about yesterday
that's right and I've nearly got over
the Williams better the thing is there
is a real conflict here and and this
pattern and essentially it's shown most
sharply in in these memory allocation
patterns and then funnily enough in the
highest level patterns the ones that are
first in the book on small architecture
which also have interesting behavior
because the point is often you think if
you are working in a memory constrained
environment you think what you want to
do or might want to do is to minimize
the absolute memory footprint of your
program okay so you're going to do the
program in such a way that it uses the
least memory possible yeah the funny
thing is that for a lot of these
programs as Charles said right at the
beginning you're in a situation where
you care about memory use in other words
you want to avoid memory memory out
situations you want to give guarantees
about memory performance so and in order
to be able to do that minimizing
absolute memory use funnily enough is
often not the most important thing the
most important thing is to be able to be
predictable about memories to be
reliable about memory use and so what
fixed allocation will say is look you
know for anything before I don't know
the number of speed-dial numbers in my
mobile phone right um I'm not just gonna
call malloc every time I want a new one
well and then when the malloc eventually
fails and there's no memory left I'll
just return an arrow stick up a dialog
box that says sorry I can't store great
auntie Ethel's number because I'm out of
memory what it says is I will decide at
the beginning that this is sufficiently
important that I'm going to have ten or
a hundred slots that are allocate all
the space that I might need for those
slots in the design right up front in
the design of the system and then the
catch is as a programmer is incumbent on
me to do a bit more work
than calling malloc you know so what you
do is you really explicitly allocate an
array and you have to manage this memory
area yourself and then if somebody asked
for a slot you basically check which are
a slot as empty and you return a pointer
to that to that array slot is that the
way it works yes though it doesn't have
to be an array it could be any data
structure and it's frequently just a
single object mmm what a reminding it's
this pattern is particularly important
in real-time systems right because
whatever good things we may say about
Malik one of the problems in virtually
every implementation is that it takes an
undefined time to do an allocation
because it manages the data as a linked
list or something because typically to
be any good there must be some sort of
garbage collection going on at some
point and Malik sometimes has to do that
so I'm sure that real-time environments
have perfectly good real time Malik's
now but in general most environments
don't and so if you actually want to be
certain that a certain operation is
going to take a certain length of time
you avoid you you avoid Malik and indeed
I came across a small talk
implementation of a telephone exchange
which sounds a bit weird yeah but in
fact they achieved it perfectly well by
pre allocating every small talk object
they needed and so they knew for certain
how long each operation how long each
call was going to take didn't need to be
fast hmm it didn't need to be
objectively really fast it needed to be
a fixed maximum the other the other
place where it's important is when
software cannot fail this is a slightly
Aero satellite the the satellite or on
your mobile phone dialing an emergency
number which has international phone
people we all now know is one one two
yeah it's so when you darlin omit the
one thing that a telephone manufacturer
is really worried about is that you
might fail to dial an emergency number
die or something of the sort and then
sue them for it the point is if you're
dead you can't sue him Pantha well yes
well your ghosts will see and and that
is that is really quite a terrifying
prospect never mind that you're dead so
the one thing that the one thing that
they avoid is any possibility that that
particular operation can fail how did
they do that they pre-allocate in the
phone application all the data
structures that are required to handle
now that particular operation and of
course the trade office that if you
don't need all the data you actually
allocate it you might in absolute
numbers need more memory than you would
have needed in the best case so this
kind of pattern is especially
interesting in cases where you know that
the stuff the application does is
somewhat predefined which is again
typically for embedded systems right
well that's precisely the point that's
what I mean when I say you're not
optimizing the absolute memory
consumption of your program what you're
doing is trading that off in favor of
thumb trading off in favor of
predictability right and then as you go
through the patterns to do with memory
allocation there are a number of
patterns which do similar things in the
sense of making or perhaps not similar
things but but make that trade-off in
different places which would be variable
okay right so there's variable
allocation as that basically says call
malloc and you know our advice is and if
you go to call malloc make sure it's
Doug leaves malloc not any random malloc
and you know wearing my professorial hat
I will say that you know people have
actually done a fair amount of research
on memory allocators and using malloc
and that for a lot of situations it's
almost if you don't need predict
predictability you are going to get as
good or better performance by calling a
good malloc which is why I mentioned
that Dudley is Malik do malloc then you
would from code you're writing yourself
you know unless you're as good at
writing memory allocation code as Doug
Lee who's been doing it for 20 years now
so how has pulled allocation different
from fixed allocation pooled allocation
is halfway is a halfway house from fixed
allocation it's saying I will pre
allocate a number of things and keep
them in a pool a pool can extend
mmm-hmm but it saves the overhead of of
throwing away and reallocating
afterwards so memory was it called
memory corruption on a corporate
corruption um fragmentation right yeah
yeah and fragmentation is a problem
because it increases the time Malak
needs an auditor it on something process
to find a three spot of the appropriate
size it does that and it also can mean
that if you want a very large piece of
memory you can oh yeah there might not
be one can lose it you need to
reallocate stuff and indeed this is this
is something we see sometimes on mobile
phones with camera application yeah that
there is enough memory to store the
photograph but for some reason you can't
allocate it yeah and that is because
you've got fragmented memory so what you
then need to do is basically compact the
memory right and this is something that
you know in garbage-collected languages
or most garbage-collected languages
these days I should say most garbage
collectors are compacting garbage
collectors which essentially means every
so often you copy all the allocated
memory down to one end of the memory
leaving a huge chunk of unallocated
memory all the unallocated memory at the
other end and you can do this manually
in your programs too and you know in
programs in camera phones in mobile
phones essentially whenever you have a
large object that you need to allocate
that has to be contiguous it's got to be
a single block you can't split it up and
allocate it into into a bunch of smaller
objects so you can talk about the
difference between the maximum amount of
memory available to allocate versus the
largest single chunk
and when those numbers start getting
very different this is when you want to
start compacting memory it's the same
same is defragmenting a disk yeah yeah
but a question how do I do this um so
obviously it's easy to to move one piece
of data to another place but the problem
is that then all references to this
thing are invalid so you'd have to
somehow have a way to either have an
interaction or notify the users that
pointer he has just has been using is
now should point to some some other
place so how do we update the pointers
to that data area if you relocated in
the in the process of compaction and the
simplest way to do that is to just have
in direction Bravin so all your all your
pointers are indirect yeah okay there's
another way of handling the problem if
you're in the sort of environment which
doesn't actually support this easily
which is C++ or anything which has fixed
memory objects and that is rather if you
know that you are going to have large
and small objects both allocated it is
worth being careful to avoid allocating
small objects straight after large ones
and then D allocating the large ones
because if you think about the way that
the memory will be actually allocated
from the heap you will find that the
small objects sitting that will fragment
the memory and stop a slightly larger
large object from from being allocated
mm-hm so it's worth if you are dealing
with this it is worth avoiding
intermixing these smaller large or at
least thinking of them in terms of a
stack and deallocating the small ones as
you go along which links into a couple
of other patterns there one we've
already talked about pooled allocation
because one way to deal with this is you
have a number of pools for objects of
particular sizes they're not specific to
the type of the object you use but
rather to its size so you might have
different things that all have the same
size and they would all use the same
pool yeah
you can you can do it you can do it both
ways depending on you know how important
things like drive safety is in in
languages like Java you know you can
make a pool by just making an array and
filling it with however many objects of
a particular class and you know you
don't give up the references to them the
garbage collector won't take them away
and they're sitting there ready for you
to reuse whenever you want them in in C
or C++ you can go through and yeah you
can basically have an array of a
particular size and you can even in C++
I think you can overwrite operate a new
yeah right way to do you know you know
in order to return a particular segment
out of that array I was just going to
briefly add one of my favorites which is
memory discard which is which is if
you've got an operation which allocates
a fair amount of memory but then
basically stops one one good way to do
it is to allocate the memory in its own
heap which could be as simple as just a
a block of bytes from which you just
allocate sequentially or it could be a
separate heap and when you've finished
you throw away the entire heap and that
can be that can be a very effective way
of managing memory it means you don't
have to go around d allocating all the
objects it means that the allocation
from the heap can be really fast and
it's it's tidy which kind of moved us
from memory allocation to D allocation
yeah that's right and so with any of
these things you do have to deal with
the allocation right and in some ways
this idea of memory discard or some sort
of region based system does make the
allocation very easy and all go to come
back to the other thing very reliable
yeah it's so again with real-time
systems and funnily enough the java
real-time stand at the RTS j has got
built-in support for it if you are
willing to contort your code in order to
make use of it there are certainly some
issues with the design of RTS J and and
I think the new version coming out and
you know in another year or so is going
to be much better particularly with
regards to memory allocation but the the
point here is you may have a task you
want your software to complete and you
you're willing to bound its memory yes
you know and the most important thing to
protect the integrity of the whole
system is that that top task doesn't
overflow you can allocate a memory
region for it basically run the task in
that memory region in some cases it can
be as simple as being you know we can
just make sure that we've got a megabyte
sitting at the end of our stack and then
allocate everything on the stack rather
than and then when that task finishes
when the function returns in the RTS j
when u deallocate the method that holds
the region all this temporary
material just goes away without you
having to do anything and then next time
perhaps around the loop you reallocate
or in fact you just have this allocated
thing and you just start using it again
from the beginning and that's another
very effective way of doing this so
let's let's briefly touch upon reference
counting and garbage garbage collection
I guess which are the two primary means
I guess of managing the the allocation
of off data reference counting is
something most people are probably
familiar with it's it's common to well
I've seen it a lot in string
implementations for example you keep a
reference in the underlying object and
as users come and go they increment and
decrement that reference and when it
becomes zero the object allocates itself
they increment decrement the counter the
counter within the object it's it's good
for simple objects and simple tree-like
structures it has difficulty when it
gets into cycles where an object points
to another object which then points back
again and those reference cowntess can
never get to zero that's why it's not
used as a basis for more sophisticated
allocation schemes so and and obviously
reference counting is something you'd
have to care about if you don't have
automatic garbage collection yes if you
still want to not really do it manual in
your application in C++ for example
you'll have smart pointers which then if
you do locate this pointer on the stack
it down decreases the counter of the
object it's pointing to yes in C++ the
destructor is the place where you write
yeah
empty reference reference code and
garbage collections probably something
for a different episode maybe because
it's a huge topic I I guess it is a huge
topic and I'll mention the book on the
topic is richard jones book on garbage
collection which is I think I'll be a
link to it in the in the podcast site
maybe go to him for an interview at some
I think he'd be certainly interesting to
talk to the reason we put it here though
is a lot of people think garbage
collection is something that you have to
be an absolute expert to implement and
chances are it's only going to be done
in your java vm and doesn't make sense
plus plus
and basically we think that all of these
things are false and maybe if you're
trying to build a highly optimized
highly efficient garbage collector yeah
you do have to be an expert but if you
are in a situation where you have a
bunch of objects of different sizes and
different kinds that are being allocated
and D allocated perhaps user objects
perhaps you know things on a mobile
phone and you've got some kind of
interrelationships between them so you
know you've got mail messages
attachments the screens in some kind of
non tree structure it isn't actually
that hard to implement a simple
mark-sweep garbage collector it isn't
that hard to implement a simple copying
garbage collector you can do it
certainly in in C or in C++ and there
are times when that's actually the right
thing to do mm-hmm
okay so let's move on to chapter number
three which we build a small
architecture patterns right oh sorry
yeah of course you can read has a big
advantage so yeah let's it says three
compression so let's talk about number
three okay moving moving on we
identified compression as being one of
the big things that people use and this
is this is more of a functionality level
and we're talking about the bigger
functionality you have to know you're
doing compression within an application
yeah and I was quite surprised to find
out that they the whole science of
compression turns out to be relatively
straightforward to understand if
stunningly difficult to implement mm-hm
and we identified only three real forms
of compression which I suppose go as
sort of easy moderately easy and
difficult so the simplest one is table
compression which where you are
fundamentally saying well I think I
noticed that certain objects are more
certain patterns are more common if
you're compressing text certain patterns
are more common than other patterns so I
shall use different lengths of bits to
encode the simple ones for example I
might in
II using two bits in English and you
know use ten bits perhaps to encode some
peculiar character with with an accent
on it that never gets used and Huffman
encoding is works in exactly this way
mm-hmm
you need a table built in somewhere
either known by both the compressor and
D compressor so either hard coded or as
gzip does it you actually put the table
into the beginning of the compressed
data yep and the table contains what the
table contains the map of if I have
character a I'm going to use bit C cry
so and so if I have character B I'm
you're going to use bits so what you
basically do is you take these
reoccurring things put them into one
place install them physically only once
and then you encode the real data
structure as a sequence of like keys
that point to that table with the idea
that the keys are shorter than the data
itself indeed yes otherwise it doesn't
make much sense yeah so it's like a form
of encryption your simple substitution
cipher yeah yeah except with a different
purpose yeah okay so different
difference coding it's really quite
straightforward if you've got a sequence
of data items say sequence of prices or
a sequence of numbers rather than
sending all the data every time you just
list the differences okay so you know
you could the simplest one is an
arithmetic difference between the new
numbers you just subtract that and then
you code the difference in two you know
pack basically the difference into a
smaller number of bits using some kind
of packed data and if you want you can
send an escape code to say okay look
here is an absolute value as it's
changed so much or to resynchronize yeah
the data stream a variant of that is
when you have sequences that are the
same you can send them as run length
encoding run length encoding indeed I
was thinking about that choose our
difference coding which is commonly used
in most commonly used in the Tiff's and
the fact for edge coding then if you
think about the white things like sinc
ml work and if you're syncing your phone
or something that's effectively doing a
difference coding as well it
saying rather than sending the entire
contents of your memory storing the
entire corners of her memory will just
all the stuff that's most recently
changed and you need probably some kind
of primary key or identifier in that
case to say this is the thing that has
changed that's right in case she do and
you know this is the thing that has
changed and perhaps even and these are
the fields of the things that have
changed hmm do we talk about adaptive or
do we well adaptive compression is the
use of more sophisticated compression
algorithms than if - we talked about the
good news is we have suggested
implementation strategy which is
basically goodbye one of these things
given that's the implementation strategy
once again for some reason this is
something in some area of computer
scientists that New Zealanders seem
particularly keen on and in Witten and
Tim Bell have a couple of books managing
gigabytes is one that once again go into
these kind of things if you want to know
how these algorithms are implemented in
great detail if you don't you can
generally get a zip or either some
patented or non patient and compression
algorithm and go directly to that yeah
okay so that brings us to the secondary
storage discussion yes and secondary
storage is so familiar to us that we
tend to take it for granted ruling as a
way of saving RAM memory but we found
when we looked at it that there are a
number of very different techniques
which are in use the simplest possible
one is so blindingly obvious
you probably don't notice it which is
application switching that you don't
have all your applications running at
one time now in the palm environment for
example an app or the early symbol
environments an application would save
its entire state in such a way that you
could go to another application and then
come back to it and you were still doing
precisely the same thing in certain
limits as as it as it was when you went
away so it appears that the application
is running all the time and it actually
it switched out and back again but of
course in in any environment
a more crude version of it is that you
just don't try and run all your software
at once you don't run all your processes
at once yeah you simply run the ones
that you actually need hmm so then the
next couple of techniques here are
relatively straightforward so you know
keep your data in secondary storage in
flash chances are you don't you don't
have a disk these days but in flash or
even in the ROM in some kind of resource
files and then have a mechanism for just
loading the parts you need then out of
those things into main memory if you
can't access them directly I mean it's
nice increasingly with flash memory can
be used as ramallah storage ROM and you
know and maybe even you can address it
directly but you can get it that way and
similarly you have data files which way
back in the dear old days of tape
processing you could even you know take
your file one one bit at a time and
process it sequentially and of course
the whole pipes and filters model UNIX
uses so much and other environments
immitate is also based entirely on
sequential processing of data files so
there's there's any amount of stuff and
and facilities available to on the
handling of data files it's it's it's
probably the story of data files is
probably the story of computational
engineering as we understand it yeah
yeah moving on there are there's the
possibility of packages which in
practice in most environments we think
of as dynamic link libraries of one sort
are okay so this is the the capability
to load within the context of an
application the data that you actually
need at a particular point although in
that case data might also be programmed
that's what dll's do right so the idea
here is that you'll divide up your
divide up your application into a bunch
of these packages or these dll's
and you will ensure you only load the
package you need for whatever you're
doing at a time so in some sense it's
like application switching but being
done within an application on a smaller
granularity level Monogram
clarity and that leads us to the last
pattern which is paging and once again
you might think well how on earth you
got a page on a small device we don't
have the hardware for it and you have to
be an operating system egghead in order
to do paging yeah and once again the
interesting is the answer is you can
still do these kind of things in
software if you need to do you always
need to do paging almost certainly not
yeah but there are times where you've
got a lot of data that you've put on
secondary storage where it needs to be
accessed relatively randomly and
essentially all you do is you you know
using pooled allocation or something you
allocate a bunch of buffers now you
write your code so that it transparently
has some way of saying I need this
particular data item I'll lock that into
this cache expecting that I will release
it as soon as I'm done mm-hmm and and
then you simply have a paging system
which you know just manages that cache
so whenever there's a request for an
item if it's already there in the cache
you return it and if it's not you evict
one of the things out of the cache you
can do copy-on-write or some kind of
right marking if you like if you've got
storage you can write back to and then
replaces it with the thing the program
needs although if I look at some of
these patterns then some of them are
kind of lent themselves to be
implemented by an OS or or a runtime
system like for example garbage
collection paging things like compaction
where you have to update the references
it's nice if your infrastructure does
that for you yes and certainly you don't
want to duplicate it if your
infrastructure does it I mean once again
I should say for the skeptical if you
are if if you don't believe us about
paging I refer you to the implementation
we have on it on the website cool yeah
one of the jokes of podcast folks is
that people talk some rubbish they are
will delete that and then we'll leave it
in of course including the sentence that
will delete it so and even I and to get
that even more meta we could even leave
this discussion about deleting stuff
that we then won't delete in the podcast
and then people say it's probably
because of this James Noble again that
there is only crap on this episode well
I think I think that's really important
in some sense the most important
technique is that in the small
architecture patterns in our book is the
simplest way to make something small is
just to leave stuff out yeah that's
actually I don't see that pattern here
well that's because in the in the book
the each chapter in fact has an overall
discussion so you know the memory
allocation talks about the general
issues of memory allocation and small
architecture says well how can you
manage memory use across a whole system
make every component responsible for its
own memory use and the simplest way to
get that down is then do without the
components you know you really don't
need yeah which was a really very
elegant introduction or or you know a
transformation transfer to this small
architecture section which by the way as
a feedback for your slides that we use
here it doesn't say one in front of the
small architecture that is shocking yeah
you left it away in order to save memory
I guess it was in order to yes yeah have
space for the bullet yes okay so that's
this custom architecture yes
so and a particular interesting feature
about leaving out is how much it is in
fact done but this is you know if you
have a look at Pocket PC versus
Microsoft Windows you have a look at the
Symbian equivalents versus you know
their laptop desktop equivalents you'll
find that that quite deliberately there
is there is a lot of functionally
functionality left out such as well I
don't believe there's an entire grammar
checker for either of the word
environments and so on and so forth it's
the reason for that is probably memory
I'm not saying it's certainly memory it
might be just think couldn't be bothered
yeah and it's not so much about the
memory in order to run this thing but in
all to store all the information that
it's needed the storage and the memory
to run it yes okay so let's look at some
of the patterns in small architecture I
guess so we start again from the basic
idea here which you know in some sense
is Revere sprach notion of
responsibility where components take
responsibility for doing things and what
we're saying here is when you're
designing the architecture of your
system you should think about this as
components not only taking
responsibility for their funky
behavior but also take responsibility
for their memories yeah and then you
know you can see patterns here so the
first pattern the new one could actually
implement here as memory limit mm-hm
which says okay components taken
responsibility it should only use a
certain amount of memory how can it you
know enforce that responsibility and
basically what you do is you set some
kind of limit for each component and
then just don't let it allocate more
memory then it's been granted but that
would mean that the allocation
infrastructure has to know who allocates
memory so you have to pass on like this
pointer and says hey it's me I want more
memory well perhaps so you know the
point is that the memory allocation
patterns we talked about earlier then
can be used in the context so um here
fixed allocated area to each component
you could give a fixed allocated net
area to each component or once again on
a number of operating systems you know
there are various ways of managing heaps
for vary that variable allocation or for
any of the other patterns although I
would add that in practice this is this
seems to be done more by measurements
once off or by you know than by actual
having a technical way of doing it so so
you will say you can have so much memory
how much you actually using get it down
and then we're going to basically you
run it you simulate it you check what it
does and then based on this you try to
convince people to change their code to
make it smaller exactly and I have
certainly seen this done over months in
a mobile phone implementation for the
whole you know of the whole phone yeah
each component therefore is an
application or something you can measure
the heap size but in fact that's not so
much what's important what's important
is measuring the overall and deciding in
which bits you are going to trim and how
in order to do it
small interfaces that sounds interesting
it's rather fun i this is this this is
quite close to my heart at the moment I
was just defining an API between a user
interface component and a an engine
component the other day and I realized
just how much the choices I was making
affected how much memory needed to be
allocated and where it was kept
so it's not about making the interface
small in the sense that has fewer
operations no this is about making the
interface small so that its demands on
system memory are small let me give an
example a slightly contrived example but
supposing I was passing a photograph
between two components and I had a
function I wrote the function that said
okay I passed this this component to you
you must make a copy of the photograph
that forces there to be in the system
two copies of that photographed data not
probably a desirable thing to happen in
an environment that that has very
limited memory now in order for me to
make sure I've understood that being the
proxy for our listeners would it also
mean that if I for example want to
display a big image and I only have a
small screen in order to transfer the
whole image I would only have an API
that allows me to transfer parts of it
same is true for maybe some kind of list
box where you'd only lazily transport
the data so the interface would be
different because you'd have to be able
to request chunks itself just a big
whole thing yes and then the
implementation of the the code that's
delivering the interface could perhaps
just get it out of disk it doesn't even
store it yes so so again there's there's
a higher level design in terms of the
functionality not requiring too much and
that there's a detailed design in the
sense that by choosing the way that you
define function signatures you can make
considerable differences to the amount
of memory that must be stored yeah yeah
so a lot of these just come down to
being explicit about what memory needs
to be transferred you know across the
API and in some sense how the ownership
of that memory can now transfer so for
the photograph possibly the way you do
is you know there are at least three
options one of which is that you allow
the other component to borrow the memory
you've allocated so you have as you have
a pointer into the other moment you give
someone a pointer and you give them
permission even after the API call has
finished oh yeah to continue to access
that okay now at this point maybe then
the component you're sending it to has
to be able to come back and say oh by
the way I finished with that photo
because the other one must not shut down
and discard its memory because it's kind
of used by somebody else that's right
through the back door that's right
another one is you could do it the other
way where the second component actually
allocates the memory itself and then the
first component writes something into it
and then is done and so you know once
again the memory is transferred but now
it's like physically part of the using
component right right right so memory is
physically part of the using component
or you could have reference counting in
which case you're putting the reference
counting into the API there's an
interesting even more twisted version of
doing this which I've seen and done in a
couple of things where basically the
deal is you swap memory blocks it's a
change tomorrow you can exchange the
memory block so the deal is I going to
give you something in a memory and I'm
going to give you a memory block I mean
this works with fixed size blocks and
the deal is the API is such that when I
do that you're going to give me a memory
block that you no longer want so
streaming audio for example will do this
so I say here's here's a block of data
and I'm gonna give you I don't know 10k
of memory and the data is in this 10k
block and would you please give me back
another 10k block that you no longer
want huh but but that means that I can't
easily use for example fixed fixed
allocation where I know I have this
continuous memory area because now part
of this one of my memory might actually
belong to you because I exchanged it
with some other stuff so that makes
things a bit more complicated which is
why it's done in terms of blocks rather
than a memory area hmm yes there's a
more detailed thing which it's worth
looking at every day making sure for
example that an API doesn't require one
component to hang on to memory that
really it doesn't need any more and just
because of the allocation this is less
of a problem in Java which of course
manages references directly but in C++
if I if I return a string by as a
reference in some way and it's quite
common in C and C how its plus to do
this then you're forcing the component
that delivered the string to hang on to
it as we said before until it's
you know until it's no longer needed and
that can that can require additional
memory allocation and quite quite a
significant way which comes back to our
original idea of saying you want to make
a components responsible for their own
memory use which means designing
interfaces so that if stuff needs to be
transferred the responsibility for that
memory also transfer now so there is a
pattern that's called captain Oates
this one is Charles's favorite
definitely it's it's part of the
mythology just going outside maybe
sometime part of the mythology of the
English culture is the story of an
unsuccessful trip to the South Pole done
by Scott and and as they were as they
were limping back home it was clear that
the team were not going to survive at
least they hadn't food to keep everybody
going and the heroic captain Oates at
some point left walked out of the tent
saying I'm just going out I may be some
time and his sacrifice was to allow the
others to live or to die a little later
as it turned out it was heroic it was
hairy and
and this the captain Oates is the
concept of the heroic application or the
heroic component that gives up its
memory in order that more interesting
more relevant or more important
applications may live so say you're
writing the ubiquitous clock or you know
the the BIC witness animated screensaver
that no self-respecting embedded system
can be without often these katia and
once again often an operating
environment will having a signal that
goes goes through and says a low memory
well the simplest way to do that is you
know if your clock just to go away and
let the memory be used by perhaps
something more mission-critical like the
the IM chat client or something and i'm
delighted to say that this is now an
essential part of Symbian OS and indeed
it is built into the testing of every
single application you cannot you know
you cannot get an application passed by
the Symbian testing process
unless it gracefully gives up its when
requested to do so or unless you've got
a good reason why not need some kind of
like priority so I have to every
component needs to have some definition
of how important it is so that people
actually know who should give up things
because I mean otherwise you can't you
know automatically determine who will
sacrifice indeed yes yes and that
generally has to be done by the
controller that is responsible for
looking at all these processes and
saying which one should I measure when
should I kill in practice it's usually
the foreground application that is the
priority one another one other processes
may say I am I really don't want to be
stopped please by raising some kind of
flag but the principle behind the
pattern is if you're in this situation
if you get some kind of low memory
warning you are better off saving your
state nicely out a secondary storage or
tidying up and quitting the new you are
try not trying to fight it yeah okay
read-only memory I think is interesting
because in many embedded systems you
have ROM RAM random access fast slow
memory so you would probably have
different areas all kinds of memories
that I'd have different you know some
are important expensive some are
certainly read-only memory is in effect
memory which is part of the code that's
the usual implementation of it right the
other implementation is resource files
when they are or files that are held in
a ROM filing system exactly that's what
our yes so so in practice for
example in Java typically the way you
would do it is to have a table that is
part of the code yeah although in
practice the implementation may not be
quite what you want the actual code that
it generates may not be quite what you
want in C++
certainly constant tables for example
for decoding a quite a common idiom
constant strings are certainly used and
you know Symbian is entirely built
around mechanisms for storing those
constant strings and then I guess that
segues nicely into
the last pattern the one the only one we
haven't talked about it hooks which
essentially says and then if you're
doing ramen you think you may want to
replace or change that information by
putting in the liquidus another level of
indirection some kind of hooks in
writable storage and if you put all
access to the read-only memory through
the hooks then you've got the option of
being able to update that information in
flash or in the main ram without
actually having people to burn or
replace the wrong yeah makes a lot of
sense yes and that can be done in a
variety of ways from having files you
know located loaded looked for first in
RAM and only afterwards on ROM so which
is an idiom used quite often again in
Symbian which means that you can
override the ROM version of it but you
won't want to most of the time ok so um
this was the run-through through the
book is there anything I mean which
means we're almost basically finished
the interview so is there anything else
you wanna you want to say like a couple
of concluding words or whatever I find
I'm using these patterns quite a bit hmm
actually in practice some many more than
others
small interfaces probably most it's
quite worthwhile I find it absolutely
great that were you know that this is
becoming mainstream again so the other
thing you know we can see that this is
in fact stuff that is still current
because in their own separate ways both
you know companies like Microsoft and
IBM and son are looking at doing
versions of their platforms for a small
memory and in certain cases also pushing
things up in two languages so there's
things like the real-time spec for Java
right and the latest versions of Windows
CE and in fact if you look at the
systems and this is actually something I
find quite gratifying if you look at the
way the designs that the systems are
evolving they're evolving to support and
quite a lot of the patterns we've been
talking about so you know the RTS J for
example has got stuff in there to
support fixed allocation and variable
allocation it's it's currently difficult
to use and I think people are working on
that
and the window systems have got support
in there for pooled allocation and
memory discount and all those kind of
things built in as always sometimes this
discussion in the patterns community you
know how how much better how pattern II
a pattern really is so how much how much
you know how common is it how generally
is it usable how terrorism is it
applicable and it's quite obvious that
these things are really really
fundamental ways of handling memories so
that's really cool stuff yes indeed glad
to be up there with the forefront yeah
that's right technology as in 1950 so um
I just want to say thank you because I
think this was a really really cool
episode I really liked it
oh maybe you makes up for the other one
okay so thank you very much for being on
the show and thank you very much and
it's been great to be here
indeed sir
[Music]
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio if you want to get
more information about software
engineering radio or if you want to give
us feedback please go to our website at
se - radio dot net you can also contact
the team at team at SAE - radio net
although we prefer entries in our
comment system on the website
so other people can see what you think
software engineering radio wants to
thank Henning Poli for the intro and
outro music as well as Lipson for
providing the bandwidth this episode of
se radio as well as all other episodes
is licensed under Creative Commons
license see the software engineering
radio website for details